hey guys welcome to concept and coding
this is Shan and in the springbot series
till now we have seen how the async
annotation Works uh today I will I want
to discuss more on this as sync
annotation want to cover some important
uh interview questions also so one of
the interview question is
that what are the conditions for using
annotations to work properly so there
are two conditions which I would say
that one is that The async annotation
where we are using on top of a method
right that method should be in a
different
class uh from where it is being called
right so that is one condition and
second condition is the method on which
this asnc annotation is used it should
be public
method now the question is why so now
first let's see this example here in
this we have a class user controller
right and this is one method get user
method
when this get
invoked it calls an async method test
right so and one thing you will notice
that this using method is in the same
class in which this caller is present
and expectation is that this using
method will get run in a new thread that
is my expectation because I have used a
syn annotation on top of it but will
this work as expected no why because
these are the two condition which should
get fulfilled that this method on which
you have used a sync annotation should
be in a different class from where it is
getting called and it should be a public
method okay so this will not work as
expected because okay you have made this
method public but this is in the same
class as of this caller right from where
it is getting called it is in the same
class
okay so to make it work properly you
have to uh take this method into a
different class itself so here if you
see the output when I invoke this to get
user is run by which thread some This
Thread name so I'm put uh printing the
thread name HTTP Neo something and when
this method get invoked inside using
method test what is the thread name same
right but your expectation is that okay
new thread will get created but no new
thread is not get created okay so we
have to have this method in a different
class and it should be a public now you
can ask me right hey why why we have to
in this different class see the problem
is not here the problem is with the
framework so at back end we are using
aop so when whenever you are using at
theate async
annotation aop get involved right uh if
you have seen the aop video you might
already know that how aop works so first
step is it do
intercept and once it is intercept it
calls the proxy and then internally
proxy mil might call your
method so to to make this interception
work these two conditions is required
interception cannot work on private
methods protected method it's only work
on public methods and second
interception only works when from class
one to class two different classes get
invoke right if in the same class you
are calling a method interception would
not be able interception is not even in
the picture so only when you're calling
from uh like you have one method in
class one and you are invoking a method
two which is in class two something then
only interception comes into the picture
so because of this interception
logic you can say that interception has
Works only when these two condition met
and because of that whenever we use
annotation these two conditions should
be
met okay so this is one thing very
important and it's a very good uh
interview question also now another
interview question is how a sync and
transaction management works together
what are the
challenges so I will explain you with
different three use cases so use case
one let's say that let's understand this
use case one so I have a
class okay in this class
I am calling user service. update
user so it
is calling this method and here I have
put
transactional when I put a transaction
means transaction will get created
here so now here if you see I am doing
some update user status update first
name user first name last name whatever
right and here if you see one more thing
I am doing is I am calling one more
method in a different
class I want to do update user balance
but instead of doing it here I am doing
it here in a different class and I say
that hey at theate async let's do this
in an async
manner okay so see this one again this
class is invoking this which has at
theate transactional and within the
transactional method I am invoking a
method which is us syn
so what is the problem here the problem
here that whenever you are creating a
new
thread it do not carry forward the
transactional context so transactional
context is all the information like okay
what is the propagation level right and
whatever the different information you
have put into this transactional right
uh what is the thread pool you are going
to use and every information which is
there in the context that is not not
even passed here in the new thread so
this code this code run without any
transaction so now let's say that any
issue comes in this
method all the roll back will happen for
this you have updated user status roll
back will happen you have updated first
name roll back will happen right
whatever but here if you are updating
the balance amount into this using roll
back will not happen this because this
is not running in a transac
ction okay so transaction contexts do
not transfer from colar thread to a new
thread right so this is use case which
should be avoided it will not work why
transaction context is not carry forward
to this async
method use case two understand this use
case now you have this class in this
class you are invoking a user method now
on this user method uh update user
method itself you have both at theate
transaction atate
oring and you are doing all the
operations inside this updating user
status updating first name or whatever
whatever the update you wanted to do but
you have transactional and adorate anot
annotation
together is there any
problem so problem is that use with
precaution when can I say used with
precaution mean first
thing okay a new thread will be
created a new thread will be created in
which this update user will work now
since also it has at theate transaction
so means all this code will run in a
transaction only okay so if any issue
will happen roll back will happen but
why I mention that use with precaution
it
because because of of this using the
transaction context will not carry
forward now suppose I have also put at
the transactional
here right and there are you know that
there are different propagation level of
transaction supports not supported right
you already know that we have already
seen different type of propagation level
is there those will not work as
expected right because even though you
have uh
use transactional and because but
because of this at theate async
annotation whatever the transaction
context you have said before that is of
that do not get carry forward at
all so this will run in a new
transaction okay so that's why I
mentioned in a yellow and put that use
with precaution as new thread will be
created and have transaction management
but context is not same as the parent
one if parent also has a
transaction right and here I am using
that okay propagation is let's say
whatever supported right so if parent
transaction is there use the same one
now this will not work as
expected right so that's why I say that
use with precaution because parent
transaction context is not carry forward
here because of this async annotation
this is use case 3 is the very safe way
and most popular way in the industry of
using it how so you have a user
controller class here if you see that I
am calling a method update user now here
if you see that this update user first I
have used an using update user now what
happen is your main thread is free it
can proceed further it do not have to
wait for update user now it's created a
new thread and now update user now I
have called
update user in this utility and here I
have put at that transaction so now
everything runs in a transaction
anything fails roll back will happen but
what I have make sure that a separate
thread is used to do this transactional
work and my main thread is free totally
so this is the correct way of using and
this is the industry standard so
whenever any question comes how you will
use a sync annotation with
transaction tell them the issue with
first doing this transaction and then a
SN or both together what are the
challenges and which one is the correct
way of doing
it okay now another topic is a sync
method return
type so to understand this
properly please do check out in the Java
playlist this video future callable and
completable future this already more
than 1 hour video right this video I
have already covered this in Java
multi-threading future callable
compatible future it's 1 hour plus video
and I have covered in depth so covering
here doesn't make sense because it's a
Java uh topic and I have already
explained in 1 hour plus in depth of
this so check out the Java playlist you
will get better understanding of this
future callable and completable future
but but I will tell you that uh how we
can use it like by joining it with the
spring boot so it will make more sense
so let's say I'm using future and just
for your information this future is now
deprecated now completable future is
mostly used in the
industry so here if you see that the
thing is when you are using an atate Ur
sync annotation we know that it will
create a new
thread right so this is your main thread
and by asking annotation it will create
a new thread let's say thread
one so if you
want to retrieve the output of this
thread one whatever the thread one has
one work upon if if you want to get an
output right that's where this future
and completable future comes into the
picture right so now here if you see
that this performed task using method I
have put at the a syn now it it it has
to return a string but since it's an a
syn I have wrapped into a
future so now this is the caller method
so when this method get invoked I am
calling this perform aing task a new
thread will get invoked which will work
and It ultimately return this async
result right this is a future
now in the I can take this uh
result in this one now maybe it will
take let's say uh 15 seconds to complete
it's okay our main method will just uh
take a reference of this and continue
forward continue its work now whenever
you will do that on this future object
uh which you have result. getet now our
main thread will wait here till the
output is a ailable now let's say that
it is waiting like to get this uh task
completed so it will wait here now our
main thread will wait at this point when
we do dot get till this method is not
completed and once it is
completed it will return
this dotg will return this string
whatever
internally right and you can print
it so this is one way of returning
from an async method if you have a
return type you can use future so this
uh like this is one of the method get
there are so many methods like get done
is is
cancelled all right and get with the
timeout that I have covered in the Java
video in depth what all functionality
you can do so that is out of scope for
this video but uh this is just to uh
provide how you can use it uh in this
way
similarly completable future which was
introduced in Java 8 the similar way you
can say that complet completable future
is just an enhanced version of
future so here in this method now
instead of future I am returning
completable future the same no code
change here it is invoking it it is just
taking a reference of this completable
future now main thread can continue its
work without stopping now at this time
when you're doing get it will wait wait
for whom wait for this method to
actually get completed once it completed
it will get its output this
one and you can print
it
okay so do check out this video to get a
better understanding of completable
future completable future is very very
important and it's not like 5 10 minutes
topic you will see a in-depth discussion
how the chaining happens in this one
supplier saying there lot chaining is
very good capability of compatiable
future do check
out okay another important interview
question is exception handling why
important I'll tell you one interview
question here
is okay you have an as syn
method which returns white let's say
method one which do not return
anything now since you have used at the
rate using it is going to run in a
different method now if any exception
comes here how you going to handle that
because your main method you have
already you have invoked this and you
have proceed further you have proceed
further but if any exception comes into
this new thread how you going to handle
it that is very important interview
question so I'll tell you this one but
the first is very simple method which
has return type
you know how to handle it so whenever
you are doing
dotg this is the time if there is any
exception in this using method it will
throw at this point of time when you do
dot
get so at this point of time you have
invoked the you have you have invoked
the assing method now main method
proceed further now if any exception
comes only when main method do get at
this point of time it will throw an
exception and you can catch it and
handle it like you want it you want to
log it log it you want to print it print
it or whatever you want you want to
throw exception throw it so this is very
very simple when the method has a return
type we can have a completable future or
future reference and using get we can
catch
it but this is where the interesting
things Li is method which do not return
anything so I have a method which
returns wide and this is calling this
method now if any exception comes here
let's say I'm trying to do 1 divide by 0
some exception comes
here how this main thread because main
thread has just invoked and proceed
further now how I will handle this
exception how I will do logging or how I
will make sure that some exception get
thrown so there are two ways to handle
it one is you use a TR catch block
inside this at the rate ass
sync so here if you see you will perform
some task now if any exception comes you
will catch it so the catch is within
this method itself a sing method so you
will catch this and handle the exception
here you want to log it just log
it
right but I'll tell you what is the
industry
uh what this industry follows and I I
I'm thinking this is the better way to
handle it rather than putting Tri catch
into the each and every ass sync method
so what happened so before I'm telling
you
this this see this one is spring boot
framework code so spring boot has
created one class internally simple
async uncut exception Handler which
implement this interface a sync
uncut exception Handler
and it has one method handle uncut
exception and it will just log it
unexpected exception occurred invoking a
sying method so now let's say that I
have this
method a sying
method and it is let's say I purposely
doing this 5 divid by 0 so we know that
it's going to throw an
exception so now I don't have any try
catch here so what would happen is
spring boot this method this class get
invoked so simple assing C exception
Handler which is a child of this
interface handle uncut exception will
get invoked and it will print this
unexpected exception occurred unexpected
exception occurred invoking a sying
method and this is the method name and
this is the exception which it prints so
it prints the complete exception and
also the method
name but
you you can say that hey I this is I
don't want this I want custom handling I
want my custom handling where I might
have different logic than just doing
this so now you got one hint that if
spring boot can implement this why not
we and do our custom so that's what the
solution is so here we create one class
I have created this default us sync
uncut Handler
which implement this using uncut
exception Handler and I have override
this method handle uncut
exception and here I am doing like in
default I just printed you can handle it
like you
want right so this is the default
handling which I wanted when any
exception occur in an N sying
thread okay so this is I created but I
need to make sure that my
this this class get invoked how you can
make sure that so in this app
configuration class you just need to
implement this ass sync
configur and what you have to do
is in this method you have to return
this object right this using C exception
Handler so I have done
autowired and this object this class so
now when you have done Auto you know
right what spring boot will try to do
spring boot will try to see that hey if
there any Bean present for this one so
see here I have created one class with
atate component you can have in this or
in this class or in a different class
also but here I have atate component on
this one right so Bean is already
created so this will get set here and
whenever in the spring board it will do
get a sync uncut exception Handler it
will return this one so mine will get
return so you got this part how you can
configure your own custom exception
Handler in case
of method where return type is
wide for an a sync
annotation right just check this out the
flow this is very simple you just have
to over right one
and this Bean will be uh get initialized
here because we have done Auto add and
we just have to return it whenever means
spring is asking we are returning this
one okay and here if you run this 5 / 0
you will see that in default uncaught
exception method which I printed not the
spring
one so in the spring one I have put
empty app config just for showing that
if if you don't handle yourself a spring
will take care of
it okay so based upon your business
requirement either go for uh
implementing the default or you can use
try catch like depending upon your
business
requirement okay so these are some
important interview questions of the
async which I wanted to cover today and
we'll see you in the next topic of a
springboard thank you bye